# Bert de Bruijn

Panaire, Caribbean Netherlands

**in** lpdebruijn

G debruijn

# Summary \_

Results-oriented and experienced Data Scientist with a PhD in Econometrics (specialization in Bayesian Econometrics and Forecasting). Dedicated to driving innovation and delivering measurable business impact by translating results into insights for end-users. Experience in Bayesian hierarchical modeling, creating reproducible Docker-based Python workflows, developing Modeling Strategies, and setting up CICD frameworks.

# **Work Experience**

#### Nielsen Media Research, Lead Data Scientist

- Successfully transforming the product offering to align with client needs and campaign specifics, introducing new tailored solutions for diverse campaign structures. Achieving a substantial increase in overall sales.
- Analyzing past product studies identifying key insights, to craft a thought-leadership piece.
   Communicating campaign components in client-friendly terms, enhancing industry credibility and trustworthiness.
- Acting as an independent researcher conducting research into new product offerings.
   Scoping out new products and product extensions (prototyping).
- Advising and assisting team members and other internal stakeholders on current and future products.
- Acted as people manager and driving development of other data scientists.

#### Nielsen Media Research, Senior Data Scientist

- Created a modeling strategy to solve common problems and challenges in projects increasing the quality and consistency of the delivery.
- Developed and implemented an "AWS Runner" for seamless cloud-based project runs, improving efficiency and consistency during the model-exploration phase in response to project scope expansion.
- Established comprehensive versioning, testing, and documentation processes through Gitlab CICD, ensuring consistency, and quality, and facilitating future development.
- Drove the analytics and programming of a team that measures the effect of media and advertisements on TV tune-in or consumer satisfaction KPIs.
- Incorporated cloud computing (including CI/CD) and reproducible code workflow (using Docker) into our project workflow.
- Acted as people manager, engaging in thesis supervision and driving the development of data scientists. Set goals for the R&D initiatives.

#### Nielsen Media Research / Pointlogic, Data Scientist

- Built and improved respondent-level models for measuring the effect of media/advertisements on TV tune-in or consumer satisfaction KPIs.
- Wrote code and made decisions around sample representativeness, data quality, controlling for confounding factors, testing assumptions; and translated results into client insights.
- Led the team transition of R to Python; set up internal Python package and initial Docker image for reproducible code.
- Created a hierarchical model for consistent full-season ad evaluations for a sports network
  that provided a cohesive narrative across the season while retaining granularity for
  individual games, meeting client expectations, and facilitating detailed analysis of
  advertising impacts.

#### ABN AMRO Bank, Modelling Analyst

 Modeled credit risk to determine a provision norm to mitigate the risk of recessions by holding reserves.

#### Sundio (now known as Sunweb Group), Data Scientist

Created a Demand Forecast model for travel bookings.

Rotterdam, NL Nov. 2021 to Jan. 2024 2 years 2 months

Rotterdam, NL Feb. 2019 to Oct. 2021 2 years 9 months

Rotterdam, NL Sept. 2017 to Jan. 2019 1 year 5 months

Amsterdam, NL Aug. 2016 to May 2017 10 months

Rotterdam, NL July 2016 to July 2016 1 month

## Skills

Programming: Python, R, MATLAB, Java, SQL, Stan

**Python packages and tools:** Pandas/Polars, Numpy, Numpyro/JAX, Statsmodels, Pypy, Matplotlib/Seaborn, & many others **Statistics and methodology:** Bayesian statistics, Time Series analysis, Regression models, Panel models, Survey design, Classification models, Hierarchical/multi-level models

OS: Ubuntu/Linux, Windows, Mac OS

**Other tools:** Git, Gitlab, AWS, Docker, LaTeX, Bash **Languages:** English (Advanced), Dutch (Native)

Strengths: Problem-solving, creativity, communication skills, organization skills, customer orientation, collaboration

## **My Personal Projects**

Advent of Code: Participating in Advent of Code (2019 to 2023 fully complete)

**Various personal coding challenges:** Examples include "Solving Sudoku with Z3", "Modeling excess deaths during covid", "Estimation and simulation of a football season"

## **Interests And Future Skills**

**Forecasting Earnings Forecasts** 

**Managing Sales Forecasters** 

Bert de Bruijn, Philip Hans Franses DOI: 10.2139/ssrn.2184281 ☑

Path-finding algorithms and other optimization techniques: Dijkstra, A\*, BFS, DFS, Dynamic optimization, etc

Runtime optimization ("running code fast!"): Pypy, Numba, Polars instead of Pandas, etc

Automation: Using GPT/Bard for tasks, auto-scraping websites, Makefiles, etc

### **Education**

PhD E	rasmus School of Economics / Tinbergen Institute, Econometrics  • Title of PhD thesis: Essays on forecasting and latent values.	Rotterdam, NL Sept. 2011 to Dec. 2015
MSc E	• Cum Laude. Title of MSc thesis: Evaluating the rationality of sales forecasts.	Rotterdam, NL Sept. 2010 to July 2011
BSc E	<ul> <li>rasmus School of Economics, Econometrics and Operations Research</li> <li>Cum Laude. Title of BSc thesis: Content horizions of Dutch election polls. Major: Econometrics. Minor: Highlights of Psychology.</li> </ul>	Rotterdam, NL Sept. 2007 to July 2010
VWO S	tedelijk Gymnasium Schiedam, VWO/Gymnasium - NT/NG  • Cum Laude.	Schiedam, NL Sept. 2000 to July 2006
Publications		
A novel approach to measuring consumer confidence Rene Segers, Philip Hans Franses, <i>Bert de Bruijn</i> DOI: 10.1016/j.ecosta.2016.11.009		Sept. 2017
Benchmarking judgmentally adjusted forecasts Philip Hans Franses, <i>Bert de Bruijn</i> DOI: 10.1002/ijfe.1569 ☑		Oct. 2016
Heterogeneous Forecast Adjustment  Bert de Bruijn, Philip Hans Franses  DOI: 10.1002/for.2433 ☑		July 2016
Stochastic levels and duration dependence in US unemployment  Bert de Bruijn, Philip Hans Franses  DOI: http://hdl.handle.net/1765/78710 ☑		Sept. 2015
Analyzing fixed-event forecast revisions Chia-Lin Chang, Bert de Bruijn, Philip Hans Franses, Michael McAleer DOI: 10.1016/j.ijforecast.2013.04.002 ☑		Oct. 2013

Jan. 2013

Dec. 2012